[♪ opening theme song playing]
[bleating]
[GIRL] My lady, where are you?
My lady!
[sighs]
Goodness,
what are you doing out here?
It's time for you
to get ready to leave.
[TÖREGENE]
Be right there.
[wind blows]
[TÖREGENE]
Farewell, Naiman.
♪
[TÖREGENE] As someone born
into the Naimans
whose nation lay far
to the west of here,
it was arranged that I would
marry into the Merkits,
with whom we shared an alliance.
[GIRL] I wonder about
the Merkit tribes
and what their lives are like.
[TÖREGENE'S SISTER-IN-LAW]
They live in the woods
just to the north.
Many of them are skilled bowmen
called Mergen.
Mergen?
They're known
as the Mergen people,
hence the name "Merkits."
[TÖREGENE] In other words,
barbaric hunters.
[Töregene's sister-in-law
sniffles]
[TÖREGENE]
Well, it matters not.
I am nothing
but a valuable gift.
No different
from a precious gemstone
or a fine fur pelt.
But that's all well.
I'm fulfilling my role,
and accept it with pride.
[senior wife chuckles]
[TÖREGENE] So this is where
the Merkits live.
It's much drearier
than I expected.
[indistinct chatter]
[TÖREGENE]
Why are there so few men?
-[DAYIR] Töregene.
-Uh?
Glad you're safe.
I am sorry, I know this isn't
much of a welcome.
Are you startled to learn
your husband's such an old man?
No.
Well, so be it.
Marrying a much older man
is far from rare.
And yet,
after our wedding ceremony,
Dayir never made any advances.
On the contrary...
So, you'll be going away again?
Please forgive me
for always leaving you behind.
And why do we keep moving camps?
It seems like
we just arrived here.
[Dayir sighs]
We can't stay
in one place for too long.
-You had best get going now.
-[gasps]
[DAYIR] Chuu!
-If you need anything, I'm here.
-Thank you.
-I, uh--
-[GIRL] Mistress...
What should I do with this?
Oh, well, let's see now.
[TÖREGENE]
Do all of the other tribes
keep moving their camps
as often as we do?
-Right over there. Please.
-[TÖREGENE] No.
There's something strange
going on here.
It feels as if we're fleeing
from something.
Well, I suppose
there's no use in worrying.
I'm only here to be a gemstone.
And what good would it do
for a gemstone to be concerned?
[breathes uneasily]
I want to go back to Naiman.
[birds chirping]
-[bird screeching]
-[Töregene pants]
They won't notice
if I go missing.
I know Chieftain Dayir won't.
Nor will anybody else
who's in the tribe.
-[GIRL] Hold on!
-[Töregene gasps]
Stay right where you are!
[gasps]
[panting]
That was close, wasn't it?
Are you all right?
You truly live up
to your title of Mergen.
Ah, not really. Easy shot.
Huh? Oh my...
You must be Töregene,
aren't you?
Then that means
you're my new mother.
[TÖREGENE] Huh?
My name is Khulan.
I'm Dayir's daughter.
Qultuqan...
Is my name.
-[chuckles softly]
-[Khulan laughs]
[TÖREGENE]
Khulan was Dayir's child.
And Qultuqan was the child
of another chieftain.
[KHULAN] See that? If you start
going down this river,
it splits off into the Qara
and Dal rivers.
Further down,
both of them wind around
until they feed
into the Selenge River.
And that's the place where
Qultuqan and I were born.
You were?
If you go all the way
down the rivers,
do you know where every single
one of them ends up?
[TÖREGENE] Hmm...
[Khulan grunts]
So you know
the star to the north
that doesn't move at all?
♪
[KHULAN] Right underneath it,
there's the biggest hole
you can imagine.
And that's the place
where the rivers from
all over the entire world flow.
Wow. I've never heard
that before.
[Khulan chuckles]
Well, it's not like
you've seen it for yourself.
Come on. Cut it out.
Is that true?
Neither of us
has the power like a kam
to communicate with spirits.
My father is a kam, though.
And he has been out
where the rivers
end a lot of times!
His soul turns into a bird,
and he flies way up there.
A kam?
Hmm. I wish
I could do things like that
and have kam powers, too.
Or be somebody who has
great skills with a bow.
You are a pretty terrible shot.
Enough! Hold your tongue!
You said it yourself, Khulan!
-[KHULAN] I'm serious.
-[QULTUQAN] So am I.
[Töregene laughs]
It looks like
we got you laughing.
[TÖREGENE]
Oh, pardon me. [laughs]
[Khulan laughs]
[Qultuqan laughs]
♪
[TÖREGENE] On that day,
it seemed like something
deep inside had changed.
♪
It felt as though
the very world around me
stirred my soul
in so many different ways.
I experienced
true laughter and joy.
Discontent and a sense
of sorrow too.
♪
As the days passed by,
I came to love
every moment here.
And then for the first time,
I understood.
Wake up, everyone!
We must flee.
What happened?
Our chieftains' armies
have been bested!
-[all gasp]
-The enemy will be here soon!
-[horse neighs]
-[grunts]
[soldiers yelling distantly]
[screaming]
Into the woods!
[panting]
[QULTUQAN]
Khulan, Töregene, come this way.
[KHULAN] Qultuqan!
[people crying]
[QULTUQAN'S BROTHER]
How much did they plunder?
[QULTUQAN]
Qudu's family is gone,
as are Chilaun's wife
and children.
[DAYIR] Töregene!
[KHULAN] Father, you're here.
[DAYIR]
You must have been scared.
I want to thank you
for protecting our Khulan.
Mm-mm.
She was the one
who protected me.
What on earth is going on here?
So, the Naimans never told you
of the danger
we have been facing?
Well, I suppose
I cannot blame them.
Our people have a true enemy.
Temüjin of the Mongols.
The vicious man who now bears
the title of Genghis Khan.
Genghis Khan?
[DAYIR]
As long as I can remember,
we Merkits have engaged
in skirmishes with the Mongols.
They have taken many
of our families
and deprived us
of our possessions.
Yet we always
struck back in kind.
But with Temüjin
as their leader, it all changed.
And the very balance
of the steppe was lost.
The reason you were
given away
to become the wife of an old man
was to strengthen our alliance
against the Mongols.
That said, it seems the end
may finally be near.
Say, brother,
if the Mongols do win,
what will become of us then?
You have to ask?
They'll slaughter the men
and take all our women
and children.
[QULTUQAN] I'm really afraid.
I don't want to die.
[QULTUQAN'S BROTHER] Fool!
You call yourself a Merkit man?
[Dayir sighs]
[MAN] Usun.
Usun.
Usun. Means "flowing river."
For his role as our kam,
the earth bestowed
that title upon him.
Listen well.
No one is to utter
a word until I've finished.
For I shall beseech
the spirits to guide me.
[wind blows]
[DAYIR] Oh, spirits,
lift me up to the heavens.
Show me what lies in our future.
[inhales deeply]
[♪ drum beating]
[breathing heavily]
[wind blowing]
[exclaims]
♪
[gasps]
[Dayir exclaims]
♪
[Dayir groans]
Usun.
[Dayir pants]
Khulan, are you there?
[Khulan gasps]
Yes, I'm right here, Father.
I could see a very lush steppe.
A river branching
and feeding into many others.
And when I followed the river
to its source,
atop a mountain that was
as tall as the heavens,
I found a pure riverhead.
All those rivers
were bloodlines.
And they signified
that Mongol progeny
will soon be spreading across
this great land.
So...
We are destined to lose
to the Mongols.
[all exclaim]
Then does that mean
each one of us
is going to be killed?
No. I won't allow that
to happen.
[Khulan gasps]
[DAYIR]
According to the spirits,
the Merkit blood will live on
even after we've
surrendered to them.
Do you really think Genghis Khan
will show us any mercy?
Yes, but we'll have to give
appropriate tribute
in exchange
for such a thing, of course.
[all sigh]
[DAYIR] A pure riverhead
to appease Genghis Khan.
-I shall offer my daughter.
-[all gasp]
Khulan.
[grunts] You mustn't!
I won't allow you
to sacrifice her.
She's a human
with her own mind and will!
Not a gemstone or a fur pelt!
[whimpers]
She's not... [cries softly]
like me.
Töregene, thank you so much,
but I will be fine.
Khulan?
In all honesty,
I am happy, Father.
I've always resented
being a girl
and needing others' protection.
But this way,
I can serve as the arrow
that will keep
each one of you safe.
You mean...
Merkits are masters of the bow.
And as a daughter
of the Mergens,
this is my chance
to take down a wolf.
♪
[TÖREGENE]
So we gathered together
and surrendered to the Mongols.
Khulan managed to sever
the chains of hostility
that had bound the Mongols
and Merkits for so long,
saving countless Merkit lives.
♪
But Qultuqan
and the other Merkit tribes
didn't join the rest of us,
choosing to stand
in bold defiance
until the very end.
Fleeing westward on foot.
♪
That should be everybody.
[WOMAN] Why did you summon
all of us here?
[TÖREGENE]
There are only young girls.
Are you Dayir Usun?
We serve under Prince Ögedei,
the third son of the Khan.
Our role is at the rear
of the army,
keeping watch over the supplies.
Ah, sounds like
I can rest assured then.
These girls are
in your hands now.
-[all gasp]
-Chieftain Dayir!
After a long discussion,
we have decided
to hand all of you over
to the Mongol nobles.
No! Why?
Come now, my dear.
You must listen carefully.
The Mongols may have
spared us our lives,
but that's where
their courtesy ends.
They haven't yet forgiven us
for past confrontations.
-[breathes shakily]
-I've no doubt
we'll soon be reduced to slaves.
But you aren't
like the rest of us.
You have your whole lives
ahead of you,
so go on
and find true happiness.
As for you lot...
Just make sure
you tell your prince
and your Khan
that these women
are no longer Merkits
from this moment forward, yes?
Do you understand me?
[stutters] I'll pass it on.
[SOLDIER] Huh?
-[DAYIR] Töregene.
-Huh?
Open your hand.
This is a Jada stone.
You can bring forth
storms with it.
Wish that I had
a better parting gift.
It's all I have left.
You've brought me nothing
but joy. I'm grateful.
[Töregene gasps softly]
[DAYIR] Farewell.
Live on with a smile.
[TÖREGENE] It was eerily quiet
in the middle
of that fateful night.
[SOLDIER 1] Ready the horses!
-Hurry!
-[SOLDIER 2] Right away!
-[panting]
-[panicked chatter]
[TÖREGENE]
The sky was burning...
Soaked in blood.
An unearthly sight the likes
of which I'd never seen.
[SOLDIER 1]
What's happening out there?
[SOLDIER 2] A rebellion.
The captives have dug in
on the mountain.
Prince Ögedei's army
is about to move out.
-That vile Dayir Usun.
-[whimpers]
You can never take Merkits
at their word.
-[TÖREGENE] Move it.
-[grunts]
-Chuu!
-[horse neighs]
[SOLDIER] Hey! Wait!
[TÖREGENE]
Even though the Mongols
had shown them
all forgiveness...
deep inside,
they had never once forgiven
their oppressors.
[DAYIR] We were raised
as hunters of the forest,
and we won't ever be
a sheep herder's slave.
Go on and find true happiness.
[TÖREGENE]
Were those words a lie as well?
No. I feel certain
that he truly meant them.
Which is why
he hadn't told me about
what he was planning to do.
Except... I'm afraid
Chieftain Dayir
made a grave oversight.
After everything else,
he failed to see
just how much...
I loved him.
[Töregene panting]
[gasps]
[ÖGEDEI] Oh, that's right.
The soul of a kam
can rise up to the heavens.
And by puncturing his body,
I only helped it escape.
A red river in the sky.
Uh?
♪
[ÖGEDEI] Who are you?
Uh?
[chuckles]
[ILÜGE] Hold on.
What are you doing here?
[TÖREGENE] Their rebellion
was put down all too easily.
I later discovered
that they'd killed Qultuqan,
and the others as well.
Upon Genghis Khan's
return from battle,
Khulan learned
of the uprising they attempted.
And the moment
she heard the news...
Uh?
My father brought his fate
upon himself with such folly.
The majesty of the Khan
is something nobody can tarnish.
[Töregene gasps]
[TÖREGENE] Khulan...
How could you say those
awful things wearing a smile?
After that,
I was made Ögedei's wife
and allowed to live.
[infant crying]
[TÖREGENE] I gave birth
to his children as well.
And the days passed by
rather peacefully.
Yet all this time,
I've been waiting...
Secretly hoping
for a raging storm to descend,
and ravage this empire.
I saved you earlier
because your smile
seemed familiar.
From that first day,
I saw Khulan in you.
After all these years,
I know how sad and powerless
she must have felt inside.
But still...
she understood what she needed
to do and fulfilled her role.
Back then, I should've known
how she was actually feeling,
and yet...
[Sitara breathes uneasily]
-So tell me...
-[gasps]
...who are you really?
[stutters] I'm, uh...
That's all right.
Regardless of who you may be,
you still can't--
I spoke
to Princess Sorghaghtani.
According to what she said,
there is an imbalance of power
between Tolui and the Kha'an.
In other words,
the empire has never been
weaker than it is right now.
Then you must be...
My name is Sitara. I am a slave.
The Mongol army
attacked our city
and killed my mistress,
then stole a book
that was precious to her.
To honor her memory,
my final duty should have been
getting her book back,
and yet...
The thought that resistance
could cause further tragedy...
That is my fear.
And it's caused me
to lead a life without purpose.
But this must be the moment
I've been waiting for.
[gasps] How so?
What could we hope
to accomplish?
♪
I have great knowledge.
If you'll allow,
I'll serve you as your
new Jada stone, Highness.
Please, just lend me your power.
And the two of us can summon
a fierce storm.
[♪ closing theme song playing]
[SITARA (ADULT)]
Next time, "Brothers."